<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root>
    <location>Brazil</location> has made important progress in slowing <action>deforestation in the <location>Amazon</location> region. As of <date>2013</date>,
    <action>deforestation</action> had declined <quantity>70%</quantity> below its <quantity>ten-year</quantity> average ending in <date>2005,</date> making <location>Brazil</location> the
    global leader in climate change mitigation. It was achieved while <object>soy</object> and <object>beef</object> production
    continued to grow, and with a large increase in land formally designated as <group>indigenous peoples</group>’
    territories. These important strides towards a new “low-emission” model of rural development are
    at risk, however. Climbing <object>soy</object> prices, the end to some of the voluntary agreements that helped
    slow <action>deforestation</action> (such as the <action>Soy</action> Moratorium), and a shortage of <object>cattle pasture</object> suitable for
    conversion to <object>soy</object>, could come together to drive <action>deforestation</action> rates back up. In <date>2013</date>, for
    example, <action>deforestation</action> was <quantity>28%</quantity> higher than in <date>2012</date>. <location>Earth</location> Innovation Institute, together with
    partner organizations, has been leading a multi-sector dialogue in <location>Brazil</location> to plug an important
    gap in the <location>Amazon</location> <action>deforestation</action> story, and prevent a reversal of the decline in <action>deforestation</action>
    rates. There are at least <quantity>eight</quantity> different processes underway in the <location>Brazilian Amazon region</location> that
    are <action>designed</action> to slow <action>deforestation</action>. However, these processes use different metrics of success,
    they operate with different spatial scales and over different time periods, and they are
    severely deficient in positive incentives for <group>farmers</group> who are doing their part to slow
    <action>deforestation</action>. In other words, <action>deforestation</action> strategies are being <action>discussed</action> in many different
    “languages”, creating an important obstacle to the convergence that will be needed to continue
    the recent trend towards lower <action>deforestation</action>. The “Multi-Sector Deforestation Agreement for the
    Amazon” is designed to help achieve this convergence. It establishes a set of incremental
    milestones for <action>reducing deforestation</action> through <date>2020</date>, when the decline in <action>deforestation</action> will
    achieve <quantity>90%</quantity> below the <quantity>ten-year</quantity> average and when all clearing of primary forest would be <quantity>90%</quantity>
    below the historical average and would be compensated by new natural forest. 
</root>
