<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="ecoSchema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<xml> 
<header><title>Climate 101: Deforestation</title>
    <author>Christina Nunez</author>
    <publication ref="NatGeo">National Geographic</publication>
    <date when="2019-02-07">published February 7, 2019</date>
    <source cat="summary" link="https://www.nationalgeographic.com/environment/global-warming/deforestation/"/>
</header>

<abstract>Forests cover about 30 percent of the planet's land mass, but humans are cutting them down, clearing
these essential habitats on a massive scale. What is deforestation? Find out the causes, effects, and solutions. 
</abstract>
<body> 

<p>As the world seeks to slow the pace of <problem probType="climateChange">climate change</problem>, <problem probType="extinction">preserve wildlife</problem>, and <problem probType="humanLifeSupport">support billions of people</problem>, rees 
inevitably hold a major part of the answer. <problem probType="deforest">Yet the mass destruction of trees—deforestation—continues, sacrificing the long-term benefits of standing trees for short-term gain.</problem>
Forests still cover about 30 percent of the world’s land area, but they are disappearing at an alarming rate. <problem probType="deforest"><extent quantity="26" unit="years" what="time">Between 1990 and 2016</extent>, <extent quantity="1.3" unit="GM2" what="worldForest"><!--A square gigameter is a million square km) -->the world lost 502,000 square miles (1.3 million square kilometers) of forest, according to the World Bank—an area larger than South Africa</extent>.</problem> <problem probType="deforest"><extent quantity="46" unit="percent" what="trees">Since humans started cutting down forests, 46 percent of trees have been felled</extent>, according to a 2015 study
    in the journal Nature.</problem> <problem probType="deforest">About <extent quantity="17" unit="percent" what="AmazonForest">17 percent of the Amazonian rainforest has been destroyed</extent> <extent quantity="50" unit="years" what="time">over the past 50 years</extent>, and 
losses recently have been on the rise</problem>. We need trees for a variety of reasons, not least of which is that they absorb 
not only the carbon dioxide that we exhale, but also the heat-trapping greenhouse gases that human activities emit.
As those gases enter the atmosphere, global warming increases, a trend scientists now prefer to call climate change. 
Tropical tree cover alone can provide 23 percent of the climate mitigation needed over the next decade to meet goals set in the <policy polType="treaty">Paris 
Agreement in 2015</policy>, according to one estimate.
</p>

 
    <sectionHead>Causes of deforestation</sectionHead>

    <p><problem probType="deforest"><cause>Farming</cause>, <cause>grazing of livestock</cause>, <cause>mining</cause>, and <cause>drilling</cause> combined account for more than half of all deforestation. <cause>Forestry practices</cause>, <cause>wildfires</cause> and, in small part, <cause>urbanization</cause> account for the rest.</problem> <problem probType="deforest">In <place>Malaysia</place> and <place>Indonesia</place>, forests are cut down to make way for producing <product>palm oil</product>, which can be found in everything from <product>shampoo</product> to <product>saltines</product>.</problem>
<problem probType="deforest">In the <place>Amazon</place>, <cause>cattle ranching</cause> and <cause>farms—particularly soy plantations</cause>—are key culprits.
<cause>Logging</cause> operations, which provide the world’s <product>wood</product> and <product>paper</product> products, also fell countless trees each year.
<cause>Loggers, some of them acting illegally, also build roads to access more and more remote forests—which leads to</cause>
further deforestation.</problem> <problem probType="deforest">Forests are also cut as a result of growing <cause>urban sprawl</cause> as land is developed for <product>homes</product>.</problem>
<problem probType="deforest">Not all deforestation is intentional. Some is caused by a combination of human and natural factors like <cause>wildfires</cause>
and <cause>overgrazing</cause>, which may prevent the growth of young trees.</problem></p>

 
    <sectionHead>Why it matters and what can be done</sectionHead>
<p>Deforestation affects the people and animals where trees are cut, as well as the wider world. <problem probType="humanLifeSupport">Some <extent quantity="250" unit="million" what="people">250 million 
people</extent> living in forest and savannah areas depend on them for subsistence and income—many of them among the
world’s rural poor.</problem> <problem probType="extinction">Eighty percent of Earth’s land animals and plants live in forests, and deforestation threatens 
species including the <animal>orangutan</animal>, <animal>Sumatran tiger</animal>, and <animal>many species of birds</animal>. Removing trees deprives the forest
of portions of its canopy, which blocks the sun’s rays during the day and retains heat at night. That disruption 
leads to more extreme temperature swings that can be harmful to plants and animals</problem>.</p>

<p>Yet the effects of deforestation reach much farther. <problem probType="humanLifeSupport">The <place placeRef="AmazonForest">South American rainforest</place>, for example, influences 
regional and perhaps even global water cycles, and it's key to the <resource>water supply</resource> in <place>Brazilian cities</place> and
neighboring countries.</problem> <problem probType="extinction"><place placeRef="AmazonForest">The Amazon</place> actually helps furnish water to some of the soy farmers and beef ranchers 
who are clearing the forest. The loss of clean water and biodiversity from all forests could have many other
effects we can’t foresee, touching even your morning cup of <product>coffee</product>.</problem></p>

    <p><problem probType="carbonGas">In terms of climate change, cutting trees both adds carbon dioxide to the air and removes the ability to absorb
existing carbon dioxide. <cause>If tropical deforestation were a country, according to the World Resources Institute, 
it would rank third in carbon dioxide-equivalent emissions, behind China and the U.S.</cause></problem>
The numbers are grim, but many conservationists see reasons for hope. A movement is under way to preserve existing
forest ecosystems and restore lost tree cover. <solution solType="recycle">Organizations and activists are working to fight illegal mining and logging—National 
Geographic Explorer Topher White, for example, has come up with a way to use <product>recycled cell phones</product> to monitor for 
<product>chainsaws</product>.</solution> <solution solType="plantTrees">In <gov govLevel="national">Tanzania</gov>, the <gov govLevel="local">residents of Kokota</gov> have planted <extent quantity="2" unit="million" what="trees">more than 2 million trees</extent> on their small island over a
decade, aiming to repair previous damage.</solution> <solution solType="politics">And in <gov govLevel="national" govRef="Brazil">Brazil</gov>, conservationists are rallying in the face of ominous
signals that the government may roll back forest protections.</solution>
<solution solType="consumer">For consumers, it makes sense to examine the products and meats you buy, looking for sustainably produced sources 
when you can. Nonprofit groups such as the <org>Forest Stewardship Council</org> and the <org>Rainforest Alliance</org> certify products they consider sustainable, while the <org>World Wildlife Fund</org> has a <product>palm oil</product> scorecard for consumer brands.</solution></p>
</body>
</xml>