<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../Github/CO2-Emissions-and-deforistaion-/xml/ecoSchema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<xml>
    <header>
        <title>Global overview of carbon</title>
        <author>ECOFYS</author>
        <publication ref="World Bank Group"> </publication>
        <date when="2018-05-01"> </date>
        <source cat="summary" link="https://openknowledge.worldbank.org/bitstream/handle/10986/29687/9781464812927.pdf?sequence=5=y"/>
   
    </header>
    
    <abstract>
        pricing initiatives As of 2018,5 45 national and 25 subnational
jurisdictions6
are putting a price on carbon,
as shown in Figure 4.7
Carbon pricing initiatives
implemented and scheduled for implementation
would cover 11 gigatons of carbon dioxide
equivalent (GtCO2
e) or about 20 percent of global
GHG emissions, as displayed in Figure 5, compared
to 8 GtCO2
e or about 15 percent in 2017.8
    
    </abstract>
    
<body>

    <p>
        This increase primarily due to the expected coverage
of the <place>China</place> national ETS. While this trend brings
the global coverage of GHG emissions closer to
the Carbon Pricing Leadership Coalition’s (CPLC’s)
target of 25 percent by 2020, further progress will
be needed to reach this goal.9
Carbon prices vary substantially, from less than
US$1/tCO2
e to a maximum of US$139/tCO2
e, as
shown in Figure 6 and Figure 7. Most initiatives saw an
increase in their 2018 price levels compared to those
in 2017. One substantial change was the growth in the
European Union Allowance (EUA) price from €5/tCO2
e
to €13/tCO2
e (US$7/tCO2
e to US$16/tCO2
e) as more
certainty developed on the future of the <place>European
Union (EU)</place> ETS in the post-2020 period. In addition,
<problem probType="budget">planned tax rate increases</problem> occurred, including
the escalation of the <place>France</place> carbon tax rate from
€30.5/tCO2e to €44.6/tCO2e (US$38/tCO2e to
US$55/tCO2e) and the <place>Switzerland</place> carbon tax rate
from CHF84/tCO2e to CHF96/tCO2e (US$88/tCO2e
to US$101/tCO2
e). Despite these developments over
the past year, most jurisdictions have carbon prices
that are substantially lower than those needed to be
consistent with the Paris Agreement, as displayed in
Figure 7.
    </p>




    <sectionHead>Goverment policy on carbon pricing</sectionHead>
    <p>
        <solution solType="politics">Governments raised approximately US$33 billion
in carbon pricing revenues in 2017,</solution> the source of
which was allowance auctions, direct payments
to meet compliance obligations and carbon tax
receipts. <solution solType="politics">This represents an increase of nearly
US$11 billion compared to the US$22 billion raised
in 2016.</solution> Reasons for this increase include auction
revenues from the newly launched <place>Ontario</place> ETS and
revenues from the new carbon taxes in <place>Alberta, Chile</place>
and <place>Colombia.</place> Existing initiatives also contributed to
this trend, including a larger number of allowances
bought at auctions in the <place>California</place> ETS combined
with higher auction sale prices,10 and an increase in
the EUA price and the carbon tax rate in <place>France</place>. The
EU ETS remains the largest source of carbon pricing
revenues due to its size, followed by the carbon
taxes in , <place>Sweden</place> and <place>Japan,</place> as illustrated in
Figure 8
.</p>
    

</body>

</xml>
