
<?xml-model href="ecoSchema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<xml>
    <header>
       <title> NASA's Ecosystem Spaceborne Thermal Radiometer Experiment on Space Station (ECOSTRESS)</title>
        <author>Esprit Smith</author>
        <publication ref="NASA>"></publication>
        <date when="2019-08-28"></date>
        <source cat="summary" link="https://climate.nasa.gov/news/2909/nasas-ecostress-detects-amazon-fires-from-space/"/>
    
    </header>  
    
    
        
    <abstract>
    captured imagery of fires in the Amazon regions of
        Brazil and Bolivia on Aug. 23, 2019.
    The red areas in the images - in eastern Bolivia and
        northern Brazil - are where surface temperatures exceeded the maximum
    measurable temperature of the instrument's sensor (approximately 220
        degrees Fahrenheit, or 104 degrees Celsius), highlighting the burning
    areas along the fire fronts. The dark, wispy areas indicate thick smoke - thick enough to
        obscure much of the fire from view. The measurements cover
    areas of about 77 by 77 yards
    (70 by 70 meters) each, or about the size of a football
    field. 
    </abstract>
    
    <body>
        
        <sectionHead>ECOTRESS and satalite observation</sectionHead>
    <p>
        The primary mission of <org>ECOSTRESS</org> is to measure the temperature of
        plants from the vantage point of the <place>International Space
        Station.</place> However, it can also detect other heat-related
    phenomena like heat waves, volcanoes and fires. Due to the <place>space
        station's</place> unique orbit, <org>ECOSTRESS</org>
    acquires <solution solType="research">imagery of the same areas at different times of day as it
        passes by overhead - instead of crossing over each area at
    the same time of day like satellites in some other orbits do.</solution> This is
    particularly important when trying to acquire cloud-free imagery over
    perennially cloudy areas like the <place>Amazon.</place>
    </p>
    
    <sectionHead>Nasa's satlite reaseach on the Amazon</sectionHead>
    <p>
        <org>ECOSTRESS</org> launched to the <place>space station</place> on June 29,
        2018.
    <org>NASA's</org>
    <place>Jet Propulsion Laboratory</place> in <place>Pasadena, California</place>,
        built and manages the <org>ECOSTRESS</org> mission for the
        <org>Earth Science Division</org> in the Science Mission Directorate at
        <place>NASA Headquarters</place> in <place>Washington</place>.
        <org>ECOSTRESS</org> is an Earth Venture Instrument mission; the program is managed
    by <org>NASA's Earth System Science Pathfinder</org> program at <place>NASA's Langley
        Research Center</place> in <place>Hampton, Virginia.</place>
    </p>
    
    </body>
</xml>
